<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Negro Cook's Day</title>
                <date><!-- yyyy-mm-dd--></date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Text encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Zachary Hughes</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>The Library of Congress is not aware of any copyright in the documents in this collection. As far
                        as is known, the documents were written by U.S. Government employees. Generally speaking, works
                        created by U.S. Government employees are not eligible for copyright protection in the United
                        States, although they may be under copyright in some foreign countries. The persons interviewed
                        or whose words were transcribed were generally not employees of the U.S. Government. Privacy and
                        publicity rights may apply.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="titlepage">A Negro Cook's Day</title>
			<respStmt>
                   		 <name>George S Barnard</name>
                   		 <gender>male</gender>
				<resp>interviewer</resp>
			</respStmt>
			<respStmt>
                   		 <name></name>
                    		<gender></gender>
				<resp>reviser</resp>
			</respStmt>
			<respStmt>
                   		 <name>Rosa Lee Johnson</name>
                    		<occupation>Cook</occupation>
                    		<gender>female</gender>
                	    	<race>African American</race>
				<resp>interviewee</resp>
			</respStmt>

                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <!--[NUMBER OF PAGES | i.e. x pages]-->
                        6 pages
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <pubPlace>
                            University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill
                        </pubPlace>
                        <publisher>
                            Federal Writers' Project of the Works Progress Administration [Southern Region]
                        </publisher>
                        <date>

                        </date>
                        <bibl>Barnard, George S. (interviewer): A Negro Cook's Day, Folder 1 in the Federal Writers' Project papers #3709, Southern Historical Collection, The Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</bibl>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note anchored="yes">This electronic edition has been transcribed from a digital scan of the
                            original held in the Southern Historical Collection at the University of North Carolina,
                            Chapel Hill.
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>

            <physDesc>
                <add>
                    <p>
                        <!-- Describe the physical document itself -->
                        There are many editorial handwritten notes in the margins, together with some that comment on
                        the quality of the life history. These were likely written by the reviser, and some have
                        initials next to comments. All marginalia is tagged nearest its original location in the text.
                    </p>
                </add>
            </physDesc>
       		</fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                <projectDesc>
                    <p>
                        This project originally began as a collaboration between the University of North Carolina Chapel
                        Hill's Southern Historical Collection, UNC Libraries, Yale University's Photogrammar Project,
                        and Dr. Courtney Rivard's English 317 Networked Composition Course during the 2016 Spring
                        semester. English 317 students designed the metadata schema for the Life Histories in order to
                        put into practice theories of rhetoric and information infrastructure that they had learned and
                        to mark up these Life Histories so that they could be integrated into the existing Photogrammar
                        map which visualizes the photographs taken by the United States Farm Security Administration and
                        Office of War Information. When this project is complete and all Life Histories have been
                        integrated into the project, the result will be a platform that allows users to search and
                        visualize what life was like during the Great Depression in way that was never before possible.
                    </p>
                </projectDesc>
                <editorialDecl>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>The gender of interviewees, writers, and revisers was inferred by using context clues such as
                            in-text pronouns or occupations. Gender was not capitalized throughout.</p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>When pieces of metadata were missing or unavailable, the category was left blank, not null or
                            void.</p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>Race was used as a proper noun throughout (example/ Black, White).</p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>Conventional English grammar rules were used throughout.</p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>When widow is given as occupation of the interviewee, an additional occupational tag is added
                            indicating the woman’s status as unemployed.</p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>For the geoDecl, coordinates are extracted using the Google Maps software for the locations
                            given by the life history. Coordinates are listed as (latitude, longitude) to match the
                            Google Maps’ format. If no exact location is given, an approximation is made in order to
                            improve the accessibility of search. Each geoDecl tag is also given a degree of certainty in
                            which 1 is a precise address,.75 is a given street name, .5. is a given city, and .25 is a
                            given county.
                        </p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>
                            In text tags include geolocations, changed names, occupations, and dates. Tag geolocation
                            with the tag 'geoDecl' and use lat, long format. Tag changed names with the tag
                            'changedname'. Tag occupations with the tag 'occupation'. Tag dates with the tag 'date' (if
                            the full date is given use the format when=yyyy-mm-dd within the first tag, with quotes
                            around the yyyy-mm-dd).
                        </p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>If the life history contains a page describing categorical information in aligned columns,
                            the mark-up will be tagged as tables, with corresponding number of rows and columns. If the
                            life history contains one column of header information, the mark-up will be tagged with a
                            rendition either left column or right column with the each line tagged separately.
                        </p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>This life history contains two sets of page numbers, one that matches to the number and order
                            of the pages within the document, and another whose number sequence is unknown. The page
                            number that belongs to the unknown sequence is marked as an added note, while the number
                            corresponding to the number of pages in the document is treated as the page number used to
                            mark page breaks.
                        </p>
                        <correction>
                            <p>
                                When a term denoting a racial category is given, the internal text was left as it
                                originally appears and the term is tagged with a contemporary term. When some racial
                                categories have appropriate terms that are used interchangeably, both are given. For
                                example, White and Caucasian.
                            </p>
                        </correction>
                    </interpretation>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>
                            When an interesting topic is encountered that is deemed important, the topic is surrounded
                            by a 'selector' tag to make these topics conducive to search.
                        </p>
                    </interpretation>
                </editorialDecl>
                <styleDefDecl scheme="css" schemeVersion="2.1"/>
                <tagsDecl>
                    <rendition xml:id="center">text-align: center;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="underline">text-decoration: underline;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="linethrough">text-decoration: line-through;</rendition>
                </tagsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
	<profileDesc>
	<settingDesc>
		<setting>
			<place>
				<location>
				<address>
				<street>Eufaula Street</street>
				<settlement>Ozark</settlement>
				<region>Alabama</region>
				</address>
				<geo>31.457799, -85.631763</geo>
				</location>
			</place>
		</setting>
	</settingDesc>
	</profileDesc>
	<xenodata> This is for non-TEI data.  </xenodata>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <add>
                <note type="handwritten" place="top right">AL-1</note>
            </add>
            <head rend="right column">
                <l>Dale County</l>
                <l>George S. Barnard</l>
                <l>Ozark, Alabama</l>
            </head>
            <title rend="#center">A Negro
                <corr>African American</corr>
                Cook's Day
            </title>
        </front>
        <body>
            My name is
            <person sex="female">
                <name type="person">Rosa Lee Johnson</name>
            </person>
            and I live in the "Hollow" back
            behind
            <person sex="male">
                <name type="person">Mr. Mac Pippin</name>
            </person>
            's house in Ozark, Alabama. I work for
            <person sex="female">
                <name type="person">Mrs. Laura Barnes</name>
            </person>
            on
            Eufaula Street
            <geoDecl><certainty degree="1.0"></certainty>31.457799, -85.631763
            </geoDecl>
            as a
            <occupation>cook</occupation>
            and sort of a<occupation>maid</occupation>.

            There are six of us that lives in a four-room frame house
            back in the "Hollow". There are two beds in my room and my son--
            he's about fifteen--and my nephew lives in that room.

            We pay &#36;4.00 a month for rent. When we had hydrant water
            we had to pay &#36;5.50 a month, but we has a well dug now so we don't
            use no hydrant water anymore.

            We ain't got but one fireplace in the house, but we don't
            get so awful cold in the winter-time. We ain't got no bathtub or
            toilet. We has a back-house out in the yard which we uses when
            we needs to. Electricity? I guess we don't need any cause we all
            go to bed early, but we has lamps and use kerosene.

            <p>One of the women who lives there washes, and two of the men
            they works out sometimes, so we all
            <sic>gits</sic>
            <corr>gets</corr>
            up
            <sic>kinder</sic>
            <corr>kind of</corr>
            early. I
            generally
            <sic>gits</sic>
            <corr>gets</corr>
            up about five-thirty, but don't cook no breakfast
            there at the house, and goes on up to Miss Laura's to cook their
            breakfast. I is the first one up there and goes ahead and makes
            coffee and cooks eggs and things so two of the children can get off
            to school. Then I washes all the dishes they left the night
            before and the ones they used for breakfast and cleans up the
            dining room and kitchen. And then I goes up and helps clean up
            the rest of the house, and makes up beds, and sweeps the front
            <add>
                <note type="typed" place="centered below">1</note>
            </add>

            <pb n="2" place="top right"/>
            <head rend="header">(A Negro
                <corr>African American Black</corr>
                Cook's Day)
            </head>
            porch and sidewalk and the rooms.</p>

            Miss Laura usually orders what she wants me to cook for
            dinner and I puts it on and goes on with my work. There may be a
            few things she wants me to wash out, which I does. Then I serves
            the dinner and cleans up and leaves for home about one o'clock.

            Sometimes I eats up there and sometimes I carries my plate
            home. When I does this she always fixes it up for me and she
            gives me plenty for myself, but there ain't much left over for
            anybody at home. White folks ain't as generous about their food as
            <sic>th</sic>
            they used to be.

            I usually
            <sic>gits</sic>
            <corr>gets</corr>
            home about two o'clock and don't ever have to
            go back and fix dinner, as they always eats what is left at night.
            I have to sweep the back yard about once a week. They furnishes
            me a blue uniform to use when I'm there, but I has to keep it
            clean, and I use a little white cap when I serves their meals.

            Miss Laura is
            <sic>kinder</sic>
            <corr>kind of</corr>
            old, but she
            <sic>knoww</sic>
            <corr>know</corr>
            how to get along
            with colored
            <corr>African American</corr>
            folks. She pays me &#36;2.50 a week. I gets off about
            two days during the month. I don't want any more days off 'cause
            I got no place to go except home.

            I was born in Waycross, Georgia
            <geoDecl>
                <certainty degree="0.5">31.213551, -82.354018</certainty>
            </geoDecl>
            , and my folks name was
            Smith. I don't remember exactly what month or year I was born,
            but I'm about 31 years old.

            My mamma and papa had sixteen children. My daddy was a
            <occupation>turpentine</occupation>
            nigger
            <corr>African American Black</corr>
            so he stayed in the woods most of the time,
            but came home about every Saturday.

            We lived down in Waycross for awhile and I went to school
            a little. I don't know for how long, but reckon it was about the
            third or fourth grade--anyway I can read and write some. We
            <add>
                <note type="typed" place="centered below">2</note>
            </add>

            <pb n="3" place="top right"/>
            <head rend="header">(A Negro
                <corr>African American Black</corr>
                Cook's Day)
            </head>
            always had enough corn and syrup to eat and kept a small garden,
            hut we never had much meat. I likes hog meat the best.

            We moved away from there when I was little and went up near
            Camilla, Georgia
            <geoDecl>
                <certainty degree="0.5">31.231293, -84.210461</certainty>
            </geoDecl>
            , where we farmed. The house was just a cabin
            out in the fields and we farmed<selector>"on halves"</selector>--that is, the white
            man furnished the land and mules and fertilizer and we did all the
            work. We planted
            <selector>cotton</selector>
            and<selector>corn</selector>.

            We played around the house and worked in the fields and I
            helped out with nursing the young children and working around the
            house. We didn't have many clothes, but we didn't need many--it
            hardly ever got so awfully cold down there and we had lightwood
            to burn during the winter months. We all had good times in hog-killing
            time in the fall, after the cotton was picked and the
            corn was in, 'cause there was always lots of chitlin's and hog
            meat to eat.

            I got married when I was about twelve or thirteen--I don't
            remember exactly--but I had "courted" some before that. Me and
            my husband got us a little farm and stayed there for a few years.
            We were
            <occupation>tenant farmers</occupation>
            and at the end of the year we never had
            anything except some more debts.

            Me and my first husband didn't have any children. But he
            died after about a year or so, so I moved to Ozark and got
            married again. I hadn't worked in the fields all my life but was
            sort of a house nigger<corr>African American Black</corr>, and could cook and clean up, and I gradually
            got to where I was a pretty good<occupation>maid</occupation>. Course I'm a little
            slow, account of being
            <sic>kinder</sic>
            <corr>kind of</corr>
            fat, but I keeps everything clean.

            No ma'm, I ain't got no husband right now. Well, I has got
            <add>
                <note type="typed" place="centered below">3</note>
            </add>

            <pb n="4" place="top right"/>
            <head rend="header">(A Negro
                <corr>African American Black</corr>
                Cook's Day)
            </head>
            one, but we ain't living together like we was married. He lives
            in the same house with me and the rest of them, but he don't sleep
            with me. I's quit him, 'cause he's running around with another
            nigger
            <corr>African American Black</corr>
            gal and I don't like that. He tried to kill me the other
            night--that is, he did a lot of cussin' and rearin' around--but he
            didn't mean it. I told the law about it and they said they would
            take care of him, but they didn't do nothing. He ain't goin' to
            kill me anyway. But I ain't going to get no divorce, 'cause the
            lawyer told me what it would cost and it ain't worth it. Maybe he
            will die before long and I won't have to. I ain't got no other
            fellow now and don't want one. What's the use of me keeping a
            worthless nigger
            <corr>African American Black</corr>
            for a husband when I don't have to?

            Vote? No sir I don't vote and don't care nothing about any
            such doings, cause that's the white folks' business. But they all
            does a heap of talking about it sometimes and gets real mad and hot,
            especially when they have a speeching at the Court House.

            The law? I guess we is all pretty good, cause the law
            don't ever bother us or come 'round. Yes ma'm, I likes to drink
            <sic>licker</sic>
            <corr>liquor</corr>, but I don't get much. But I likes
            <selector>gin</selector>
            the best.

            I hardly ever is sick, but sometimes I has a cold. When I
            feels
            <sic>kinder</sic>
            <corr>kind of</corr>
            puny Miss Laura she doctors me up. She's a pretty
            good doctor, but I don't like castor oil and she uses lots of it.
            We all stays right well, but sometimes they tell us to go to the
            doctor down at the Court House where they gives us free treatment
            for things.

            I belong to the<selector>Methodist Church</selector>--joined when I was about
            twelve years old--and likes to go to church every Sunday. I likes
            <add>
                <note type="typed" place="centered below">4</note>
            </add>

            <pb n="5" place="top right"/>
            <head rend="header">(A Negro
                <corr>African American Black</corr>
                Cook's Day)
            </head>
            to go to church 'cause I see all the other people, and we talks
            and prays and sings, and the preacher preaches, and sometimes somebody
            gets happy and shouts. I used to go to Sunday school, but I
            don't hardly ever go any more. We has Sunday school on Sunday
            afternoons 'cause in the mornings we all has to work. I don't
            believe in no baptising and ain't got that kind of religion
            <sic>atall</sic>
            <corr>at all</corr>.

            There's a picture show down town and I goes to it sometimes.
            Its run ty the white folks and us sits in the balcony and we can't
            make any noise cause they will run us out if we does. They
            <sic>shore</sic>
            <corr>sure</corr>
            are pretty sometimes, but<sic>pshaw</sic>, there's things goin' on right
            here in town--and some folks I knows--that is heaps funnier.

            I whole lot rather live in town than out on the farm. You
            don't
            <sic>git</sic>
            <corr>get</corr>
            to see many folks out there and has to work mighty hard.
            I likes to pick cotton, but I rather work in town and cook for
            some good white folks.

            I don't have much money, but I don't need much and
            <sic>gits</sic>
            <corr>gets</corr>
            along all right. I wouldn't know what to do with lots of money
            if I had it--maybe some other nigger
            <corr>African American Black</corr>
            would steal it from me and
            maybe kill me to boot!

            Sometimes I'll take in a wash
            <sic>ao</sic>
            <corr>or</corr>
            two when I wants some extra
            money for something special. Everything around our house is as
            clean as we can keep it, 'cause white folks won't give washing to
            niggers
            <corr>African American Black</corr>
            that keeps dirty places.

            In the afternoons when I
            <sic>gits</sic>
            <corr>gets</corr>
            home--when I ain't got no
            washing to do--I just
            <sic>sorter</sic>
            <corr>sort of</corr>
            sits around and talks to the neighbors.
            <add>
                <note type="typed" place="centered below">5</note>
            </add>

            <pb n="6" place="top right"/>
            <head rend="header">(A Negro
                <corr>African American Black</corr>
                Cook's Day)
            </head>
            Well, it's
            <sic>gittin'</sic>
            <corr>getting</corr>
            along about seven o'clock and I's got
            to go to bed so I can
            <sic>git</sic>
            <corr>get</corr>
            up in the morning and cook those white
            <sic>chilluns'</sic>
            <corr>childrens'</corr>
            breakfast so they
            <sic>kin</sic>
            <corr>can</corr>
            go to school on time. I has to
            have my sleep. But you come again and ask me some more questions.
            And
            <sic>iffen</sic>
            <corr>if and</corr>
            I thinks up anything else I'll tell you about em.
            <add>
                <note type="typed" place="centered below">6</note>
            </add>
        </body>

    </text>

</TEI>
